Welcome to the last video for this week.
I'm recording this mainly because
I want to try out my
recording technique in case I want
to draw you something in this app.
In terms of content, I'll just
do briefly what was on the slides
as well, on the point
of instantiating classes to objects.
Let's first look at the
class on the left here.
That was the Point class from the slides.
And there I already had an example,
that if you draw an object to
it, it could look like this.
So you also have a box like
that, but it only has two sections.
So there is nothing that
would correspond to these method boxes.
Instead, you simply have a line at the
top where you have to enter the
name of the object and the corresponding class.
So for example myPoint is
from the class Point, and
syntactically this is
to be underlined here.
And then in the box below
you have to specify the attribute assignments.
So in this case for x
a number and for y a number.
I could write them one below the
other, if I had left space for it.
I also allow myself to write it this way,
if I now want to assign the
two attributes x and y in the case.
So a third box somehow for
the methods does not exist, because
they are not to be created in the object.
They belong to the class and have the
same effect on every object of the class.
Of course, what we have
here now is not the
only possible object you could
have from the class Point.
Of course, you could have another
object or any number of other objects.
They would have to
have different names somehow.
They should each have a unique name.
So, for example, we could have an
object here called p2, and of course
it's also a Point object, so
it has to be specified that way.
And that can contain, for example, other
concrete attribute values for x and y.
Should of course also have
a value for each of them.
We already had something like
that explicitly on the slide.
Then there was this other slide
where we formed a subclass of Point.
So for example,
there should be ColoredPoints.
Those are also Points, but have an
additional attribute for the
color, c, and another method.
But of course, the method will not
appear in object instantiation again, because
we don't specify the methods anyway.
But what would be an
object of the class ColoredPoint now?
It could look like this, for example.
It should also have a
meaningful name, for example cp.
And of course the
class would be ColoredPoint.
And again this underlining.
And what belongs in here now?
All attributes.
And there is important:
Not only the c has to be specified.
It is also not that the
c replaces the x or the y.
But in the ColoredPoint class there
are all attributes that Point has,
plus those that
were introduced for ColoredPoint.
So a possible object for this class would be something like one
that contains x = 2, y = 3, and c = red.
And if we were to
omit those two things, for example,
then the object would
not be fully specified.
There would be missing values.
Again, this is not the only
possible object of the ColoredPoint class.
Of course there could
be several other objects.
So there could be an object, for me cp2.
So just named differently by
this number, and then also
ColoredPoint.
And then these three values x, y, c
would always have to be specified in each object.
So, as a further object here x =
7, y = 2 and c = blue.
That would be two objects of the class Point on
the left, two objects of the class ColoredPoint on the right.
So much for that.
Another observation that appeared on the
slides was the possibility of multiple inheritance.
Let's take a look
at that with this example.
So let's imagine that
besides this inheritance from
Point to ColoredPoint, there was
also a class for 3D points.
So Point was two-dimensional.
Let's assume that there should
be another class of 3D points.
What would it
have for further specifications?
At least it has
to store one more coordinate.
So x and y are already
present, because they are inherited from Point.
3D-Point would additionally
contain a z-coordinate.
Maybe also some methods.
But let's assume we don't
need any additional methods, but
work with the ones
that are already there.
It is now only a matter of
being able to store the additional z.
And it's just inheriting from above,
from the other class, from the Point
class, the other things, especially
the x and the y.
Now we would have Points, we would
have ColoredPoints, we would have 3D Points.
Now we could also imagine that
we would like to have
colored points in 3-dimensional space.
So actually a class that contains both
x and y as the two-dimensional coordinates,
as well as a third coordinate for
the third dimension, but just also a color.
Multiple inheritance would allow
us to do that.
I already said, not
all programming languages support that.
But the concept as
a modeling concept exists.
So then you
could introduce another class.
It could be
called 3DColoredPoint, for example.
And you just want to say that
it inherits from the other two classes.
So it would inherit from
ColoredPoint as well as from 3DPoint.
And that means that even
if I don't specify anything
else, this class per se already has
four attributes, namely x, y, z and c.
So an object of this class
could then look like this, for example:
It must have a name,
let's call it p for simplicity.
It should instantiate 3DColoredPoint, and
then it must occupy what attributes?
Well, all the attributes
inherited from the other classes.
So x = 3, y = 0, z
= 4 and c = red for example.
Although no attributes are specified here at
all, they would all have to be there.
Because they are inherited from the other
classes, and each from the appropriate places.
So we inherit z from here, c from here, and
x and y actually in two ways, so and so.
And we were sort of lucky that no
attribute somehow appeared in two of the classes involved.
Then you could get
ambiguity problems under some circumstances.
But here everything is
well defined, well modeled.
And we can meaningfully talk
about 3D colored points like that.